<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The French Kings edict vpon the peace which it pleased his Majestie to grant vnto all those of the reformed religion within his seuerall dominions, including likewise those of Rochell Published, and registred in the Parliament the 6.th of Aprill. 1626.</title>
            <title>Proclamations. 1626-03. English</title>
            <author>France. Sovereign (1610-1643 : Louis XIII)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1626</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 21 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06374</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16845</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108842</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844496</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844496</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9313</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06374)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9313)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 845:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The French Kings edict vpon the peace which it pleased his Majestie to grant vnto all those of the reformed religion within his seuerall dominions, including likewise those of Rochell Published, and registred in the Parliament the 6.th of Aprill. 1626.</title>
                  <title>Proclamations. 1626-03. English</title>
                  <author>France. Sovereign (1610-1643 : Louis XIII)</author>
                  <author>Louis XIII, King of France, 1601-1643.</author>
                  <author>France. Parlement (1946- ). Proceedings. 1626-04-03.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by B. Alsop and T. Fawcet?] for Mercurius Britannicus,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1626.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The edict dated: Paris in the moneth of March, in the yeare of grace 1626.</note>
                  <note>With an extract of the registers of the French Parliament dated 3 April 1626.</note>
                  <note>Printers' names conjectured and place of publication supplied by STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Huguenots --  France --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9313:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9313:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>FRENCH KINGS EDICT VPON THE PEACE WHICH IT pleaſed his Majeſtie to grant vnto all thoſe of the Reformed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion within his ſeuerall Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Including likewiſe thoſe of ROCHELL.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed, and Regiſtred in the Parliament the</hi> 6. <hi>th of Aprill.</hi> 1626.</p>
            <p>Printed for <hi>Mercurius Britannicus.</hi> 1626.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="edict">
            <pb facs="tcp:9313:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9313:2"/>
            <head>The Kings Edict vpon the Peace which it hath pleaſed his Majeſtie to giue vnto his Subjects of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended reformed Religion.</head>
            <head type="sub">Publiſhed in the Parliament the Sixth of Aprill, <hi>1626.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>EWIS, By the grace of God, King of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Navarre.</hi> To all both preſent and to come greeting. As Soueraigne authoritie hath no leſſe ſplendour in actions of Grace and Clemencie, then in Armes and Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and to know how to vanquiſh and pardon are the higheſt markes of Magnanimitie. So that a Prince ought to be eſteemed worthy of honor and glory who hauing giuen courſe to his Armes againſt thoſe which had iuſtly brought them vpon them, &amp; after they had ſubmitted &amp; ranged themſelues in their dutie is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to exerciſe his clemency towards them, &amp; to make the publike fruits to be gathered by the eſtabliſhing of Peace, which cauſeth God to be ſerued and inuocated in all places, the Kings authoritie reuerenced, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged of all, and the Lawes religiouſly to bee obſerued, the people eaſed, and the body of the State
<pb facs="tcp:9313:3"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:9313:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:9313:4"/>vniting its forces together is more powerfull for its conſeruation, and to giue ſuccours and protection to the Allies. Theſe conſiderations which we haue euer had before our eyes, haue giuen vs occaſion to vſe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much moderation to mittigate and extinguiſh the motiues which diuers times haue expoſed this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome into combuſtion, vſing grace towards thoſe who inconſiderately haue caſt themſelues thereinto, as we haue ſhewed vigour, firmeneſſe and diligence to chaſtiſe and correct them, when we were thereunto conſtrained. Concerning the preſent affaires, our courſes haue beene ſuch, that hauing imployed both threatnings and puniſhments in places which openly haue declared themſelues diſobedient, and gentlenes, patience and perſwaſions vnto thoſe which haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned themſelues in their duty and obedience, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing kept backe the tempeſt of trouble wherewith this ſtate was menaced with an inteſtiue warre and preſerued the better and greater part of our Subiects of the pretended reformed Religion in the fidelity and obeiſance wherein they are bound vnto vs: Our intention hauing beene ſo cleerely ſeene and knowne to haue alwayes beene as it is ſtill at this preſent to maintaine them in peace, concord, and tranquilitie, and to cauſe them inuiolably to inioy the graces vnto them granted by our Edicts and declarations. And that thoſe which haue taken Armes, and the Townes which haue followed their examples, hauing lately conſidered the quality of their offence, the publike indignation, the ruine and iuſt puniſhment that they draw vpon themſelues, continuing to trouble the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb facs="tcp:9313:4"/>of this State: they haue had recourſe vnto our benignity, as to the only refuge of their ſafety, and haue by their deputies beſought vs diuers limes by all wayes of Submiſſion that ſubiects may ſhew vnto their King to pardon and forget what was paſt, and to giue them peace. Whereupon, we rather inclining to grace and clemencie, than to the ruine and deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our proper ſubiects: Hauing alſo regard to the moſt humble Supplications to vs made in the name and behalfe of thoſe of the pretended reformed Religion which haue continued in their duties, that we would be pleaſed to receiue the ſubmiſſions of the others, to forgiue their inconſiderate courſes, and to reunite all in peace and concord vnder their obliged obedience. Proteſting and aſſuring vs neuer to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from the ſame, for any cauſe, pretext or occaſion whatſoeuer. <hi>Wee declare,</hi> that for thoſe and other cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and conſiderations of great importance, vs mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, by the aduiſe of the Queene our moſt honoured Lady and Mother, the Princes of our blood, and of other Princes, Dukes, Peeres and Officers of our Crowne, the principall Lords and moſt eminent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of our Counſell being neere vnto vs: We haue ſignified and declared, doe Signifie and declare by theſe preſents, Signed vnder our hand, that our will and pleaſure is,</p>
            <p n="1">I. That the Edict of <hi>Nantes,</hi> Declarations, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Articles, publiſhed and enrolled in our Courts of Parliament ſhalbe inuiolably kept &amp; obſerued for our
<pb facs="tcp:9313:5"/>Subiects of the pretended reformed Religion to inioy as they haue well and duely done in the time of the King our moſt honoured Lord and Father deceaſed, whom God aſſaile, and ſince our comming to the Crowne before the laſt troubles.</p>
            <p n="2">II. That the Catholicall, Apoſtolicall and Romane Religion ſhall bee reſtored and re-eſtabliſhed in all places of our Kingdome and Countries vnder our o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyſance, where it hath been intermitted during theſe laſt troubles to bee fully, peaceably and freely exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: Expreſſely forbidding all perſons of what quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or condition ſoeuer, vpon paine of being puniſhed as infractors of peace and perturbators of the publike repoſe, not to trouble, moleſt nor imquiet the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall perſons in the celebration of diuine Seruice and other functions of the Catholique Religion, nor of their inioying and perception of Tithes, fruites and reuenues of their Benefices, and all other rights and duties belonging vnto them, and that all thoſe who during the laſt troubles that doe detayne any goods and reuenues of the Churches appertayning vnto Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall perſons, ſhall leaue vnto them the full and intire poſſeſſion free and peaceable, conformable to the 3. Article of the Edict of <hi>Nantes,</hi> and reſtore ſuch goods taken as ſhall be found in nature.</p>
            <p n="3">III. That the exerciſe of the pretended reformed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion ſhall bee re-eſtabliſhed in the places where it
<pb facs="tcp:9313:5"/>hath beene, according to our ſaid Edicts and Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in the yeare 1620. And our Subiects of the ſaid pretended reformed Religion ſhall bee re-eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in the ſaid places, as alſo in their Churchyards or places of Burials where they haue beene granted, or others, ſuch as by the Commiſſioners which ſhall bee by vs deputed or Officers of Townes ſhall finde it moſt fit and conuenient, And where they ſhall beſt fall or for ſome important cauſe, that the places of Burials cannot bee re-eſtabliſhed in the ſame places which they poſſeſſed in the yeare 1620. there ſhall be others giuen them, which ſhall be commodious at their charges which ſhall require the alteration.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. And to giue publike teſtimony of the conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the which wee hold thoſe of our Subiects of the pretended reformed Religion, which haue continued in their fidelitie and obeyſance, and the recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable proofes which ſome of them haue demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto vs in our Armies both within and without our Kingdome, We haue at their humble ſupplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, hauing alſo had regard vnto the Submiſſions of thoſe which were ſtrayed from their duties, and by our eſpeciall Grace full power and Royall authoritie, wee haue acquited, remitted and pardoned, doe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite remit and pardon by theſe preſents, all leuies of Armes, enterpriſes and acts of hoſtilitie committed by our ſaid Subiects of the pretended reformed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, of what eſtate, qualitie or condition ſoeuer they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee, together with the Townes which haue followed
<pb facs="tcp:9313:6"/>their examples, and the Inhabitants thereof aſwell by Sea as by Land; ſince the firſt day of Ianuary in the yeare 1625. and precedent commotions vntill the day of the Publication of theſe preſents, therein compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended that which peraduenture hath hapned within the internall of the Signature of the Declaration the 20. th of October 1622. and the publication thereof in our Courts of Parliament, whereof they ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine fully and perpetually diſcharged, together with all other generall and prouinciall aſſemblies, ſmall conuentions, leuies, popular commotions, exceſſes, violences, infractions of Safegards, and all other things generally whatſoeuer contained in the 76. and 77. Articles of the ſaid Edict of <hi>Nantes,</hi> although they are not heere particularly declared and expreſſed, without being for any thing heretofore or to come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny way queſtioned, purſued nor inquieted, except onely the caſe reſerued as it is ſpecified and declared by the 86. and 87. Articles of the ſaid Edict of <hi>Nantes,</hi> whereof examination may bee made before the Iudges to whom the knowledge of the cauſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth.</p>
            <p n="5">V. And for ſuch ſummes of monies as haue beene im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, leuied, and taken vpon our Subiects, or our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipts, or thoſe who haue the managing and admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration thereof and diſcharges of thoſe which are comptable, together with that which concerneth the debts and exceſſes by the communalty of both parts, and not payd. The 74.75.78. and 79. of the Edict of <hi>Nantes</hi> ſhall be kept and obſerued.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb facs="tcp:9313:6"/>VI. Which doing all Seates of Iuſtice, Cuſtome-hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s and receipts, and Officers of Finances, which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uenture might, or haue beene transferred by means <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the preſent troubles ſince the moneth of Ianuarie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> laſt yeare, and eſpecially thoſe of the Table of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ction of <hi>Rochell,</hi> ſhall be eſtabliſhed in the ſame e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>te wherein they were. The Townes which remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d Reformed ſhall inioy the ſame priviledges, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>unities, Franchiſes, Faires and Markets, which they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ue done heretofore. The elections of Conſuls ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> made after the accuſtomed forme, and in caſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>peale, it ſhalbe relieued in our Chamber of Edict.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. In like manner, we will that our ſaid Subiects of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> pretended reformed Religion, ſhalbe wholly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d intirely diſcharged of Iudgements and Decree. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>de againſt them through the occaſion of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>t troubles, following the 58.59. and 60. Articles, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſaid Edict, impoſing perpetuall Silence vpon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> our procurators generall, their Subſtitutes and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> others which therein may pretend intereſt.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. Wee charge and command, that all hoſtile Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rs which are detained on either part, who haue not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ed ranſome, ſhalbe deliuered and ſet at full liberty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ithout paying any: declaring all promiſes made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> cauſed for ranſome, which haue not beene diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged
<pb facs="tcp:9313:7"/>by the day of the date hereof to be voide and of none effect, prouided notwithſtanding that for the ranſomes already paid, there may be no pretences not repetitions: as alſo thoſe of our Subiects of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended reformed Religion, which are ſeazed by au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Iuſtice, detayned in our Priſons or Gallies, by meanes of the laſt and precedent troubles, yea, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen thoſe that were taken in the enterpriſe of Port <hi>St. Lewis,</hi> ſhalbe enlarged and ſet at liberty immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly after the publication of theſe preſents without any remiſe or delay.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. Our meaning likewiſe is, that the 27. Article of the ſaid Edict of <hi>Nantes,</hi> concerning the admiſſion and reception of our Subiects of the ſaid pretended re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion to charges and Offices ſhalbe kept and obſerued, and that all thoſe of the ſaid Religion what quality or condition ſoeuer, which haue beene by meanes of the preſent troubles deſtituted and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of their Charges, Offices, Dignities, houſes and habitations ſince the firſt of Ianuarie 1625. ſhalbe remitted, and re-eſtabliſhed. As alſo in all their goods, names, debts, reaſons, actions, which haue beene ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed in the time of the firſt and laſt commotions; Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all prouiſions of Offices, gifts, confiſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, repreſalls, payments, and quittances: Permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the Creditors to put in execution their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts and Obligations for the principall, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all Iudgements and Areſts, except it were intervented with an arreſt diffmitiue and controdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie
<pb facs="tcp:9313:7"/>for that regard in our Counſell, or in our chambers of the Edict, or that the particulars haue beene paid elſe-where.</p>
            <p n="10">X We will that our preſent Letters of declaration ſhalbe kept and obſerued by all our Subiects, in and according to the preſcribed forme by the 82. Article of the ſaid Edict of <hi>Nantes,</hi> but Commiſſioners, ſhalbe by vs deputed where need ſhall require, to cauſe the Contents thereof to be duly executed.</p>
            <p n="11">XI. With expreſſe charge to our ſaid Subiects, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing the ſaid pretended reformed Religion, not from henceforth to hold any generall or particular <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſemblies, Counſels, conventions, nor any other of what quality or condition ſoeuer, except they haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xpreſſe commiſſion by Letters or Breefes by vs Signed and counter-ſigned by one of our Secretaries of State: &amp; that they ſhall depart from all practices, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elligences, vnions &amp; aſſociatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. It being not the leſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ermitted the collection of their conſiſtories and Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ods for the affaires concerning the ordering of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſcipline of the ſaid pretended reformed Religion, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onformable to our Letters of declaration, dated the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>7. of Aprill 1623. inacted for the holding of collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Synods, with expreſſe inhibitions to treate of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ny pollitick affaires, and from henceforth they ſhall make no fortifications in no manner whatſoeuer with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n our Townes, without our expreſſe Licence by our
<pb facs="tcp:9313:8"/>Letters Patents; Neither ſhall they raiſe any ſommes of Money vpon our Subiects for any cauſe whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, without commiſſion vnder our great Seale: vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on paine of <hi>Crimum leze maieſtatis,</hi> and to fall from, and to be depriued of this our preſent grace.</p>
            <p n="12">XII. Our intent is alſo that the Articles by vs conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, for that which concerneth the Towne of <hi>Rochell,</hi> Iles and countrie of <hi>Aulins</hi> ſhall bee kept, obſerued, and incontinently, and without delay executed, and that the Townes and Caſtles which ſhall be found to haue beene taken by thoſe of the pretended reformed Religion ſince the firſt troubles, ſhall be rendered in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our obeiſſance within fifteene dayes after the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication of theſe preſents. Declaring thoſe of our Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects of the ſaid pretended reformed Religion which ſhall make difficulties to ſubmit themſelues to this our will, to be falne and depriued of the benefit of this our preſent grace.</p>
            <p>So We giue command to our truſtie and welbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued the Officers of our Courts of Parliaments, and Chambers of the Edict, our Chambers of Accompts, Courts of our Aydes, Baylies, Seneſcals, or their Lieutenants, and to all other our Iuſtices and Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers to whom it ſhall appertaine to cauſe to be read, publiſhed, and recorded by euery one of them, and the contents hereof inuiolably to be kept and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued according to the forme and tenor thereof, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any conteruention or ſuffering the ſame to bee conteruented in any manner whatſoeuer. Enioyning
<pb facs="tcp:9313:8"/>our Procurators generall or their Subſtitutes, to cauſe to this effect to bee vſed all inſtances, purſuites, and requiſitions neceſſarie: Notwithſtanding all Decrees, Letters, and other things to the contrary notwithſtanding, To the which Derogatories of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatories therein contained, we haue derogated and doe derogate by theſe preſents: For ſo is our pleaſure. And to the end that it ſhall remaine firme and ſtable foreuer, Wee haue put our Seale thereto. <hi>Giuen</hi> at <hi>Paris</hi> in the moneth of March, in the yeare of grace 1626. and of our Raigne the 16. Signed LEVVIS. And vnderneath, By the King <hi>De Lomenie.</hi> And of one ſide <hi>Vis A.</hi> And Sealed with the great Seale in greene Waxe, vpon labelles of red and greene Silke Laces.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Read, publiſhed and recorded, heard, and which the Kings Procurator generall requiring it to bee executed kept and obſerued according to the forme and tenor thereof, with charge according to the Decree the <hi>3.</hi> of this Moneth: and that a collationed Copie of the originall of the ſaid Letters ſhould bee ſent to the Bailyſhips and Sene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſchalſhips of this Iuriſdiction, to bee likewiſe read, publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and recorded, by the diligence of the Subſtitute of the ſaid Procurator generall who are inioyned to certifie the Court to haue done it within the Moneth.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given at <hi>Paris</hi> in the Parliament, <date>Munday <hi>6.</hi> of Aprill, <hi>1626.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Signed DV TILLET.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="extract">
            <pb facs="tcp:9313:9"/>
            <head>The Extract of the Registers of the Parliament.</head>
            <p>THe Court hauing ſeene all the Chambers aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled, the Letters Patents conformall to the Edict giuen at <hi>Paris</hi> in the moneth of March 1626. Signed LEWIS, and vnderneath, by the King, <hi>De Lomenye,</hi> and Sealed with the great Seale in greene waxe vpon ſilken Strings. By the which and for the cauſes therein contayned, the King willeth and ordayneth, that the Edict of <hi>Nantes,</hi> Declarations ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret and publike and recorded in his Courts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be kept and obſerued: That the Catholicall, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolicall, and Romane Religion, be placed and re-eſtabliſhed in all the places and parts of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome where it hath beene intermitted during the laſt troubles, there to be freely exerciſed, with prohibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to trouble or moleſt the Eccleſiaſticall perſons of diuine Seruice and other functions of the Catholike Religion; and that the pretended reformed Religion ſhall likewiſe bee re-eſtabliſhed, according to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations of the yeare 1620. Acquiting, remitting and pardoning thoſe which make profeſſion thereof, all what is already paſt during the time of the ſaid troubles, as more amply may appeare by the ſaid Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters petitions of the Maior and Eſchevins of the Citie of <hi>Orleans,</hi> of <hi>Frances, Godfrey, Gabriel, Hirault,</hi> and his conſorts, Merchants of the ſaid Citie, and of the Catholicke inhabitants of the Towne of <hi>Montpeli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:9313:9"/>and places adioyning, Prelates, Eccleſiaſticall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Gentlemen and others, and <hi>Iohn Caſſeirol</hi> their Deputie, to the end to bee receiued oppoſants to the verification of the ſaid Edict. The Concluſion of the Kings procurator generall, and all which conſidered, <hi>The ſaid</hi> Court hath ordayned and ordayneth, that the ſaid Letters in forme of Edict ſhall be read, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed and recorded in the Office thereof, to be execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, kept and obſerued according to their forme and tenor: With this charge notwithſtanding, that in the execution of the 9. Article, the ſummes payd by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of guifts, confiſcations, repreſailes or otherwiſe may not be repeated, but ſhall remaine to thoſe which haue receiued them: Sauing to the ſaid inhabitants of the ſaid Countrey, to prouide for them vpon their oppoſition in the Parliament of <hi>Thoulouſe,</hi> and to the ſaid inhabitants of <hi>Orleans,</hi> to cauſe the Decree to be executed by them obtained in the Kings priuie Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell the 22. of Nouember, 1625. Ordayning that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lationed copies of the ſaid Letters ſhall be ſent to the Bailiwicks and Seneſcalſhips, to be likewiſe read, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed and Recorded, by the diligence of the Subſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of the Kings Procurator generall, who ſhall certifie to the Court their diligence within the Moneth.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Giuen</hi> in the Parliament <date>the third of Aprill 1626.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Signed. <hi>Du Tillet.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
